<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Set Things Right</title>
    <description>A digital workbench to turn my ideas into something useful</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jul 2024 08:23:34 +0200</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Jul 2024 08:23:34 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.3.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Where the puck is going to be</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Product design requires you to imagine the future version of a product, but how do you do it reliably? Ice Hockey may offer some insights.&lt;/em&gt;
___&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;ice-hockey-and-product-design&quot;&gt;Ice Hockey and Product Design&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the Wayne Gretsky quote that goes, “I skate to where the puck is going to be, not where it is”, the way to win is to accurately anticipate the future outcomes as accurately as possible. The principle could be applied to product design too. The way to design a successful product is to know what the next version of the product is going to be. But the challenge of knowing what that is as challenging as judging where the hockey puck is going to be on the ice rink.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But while no one can be absolutely certain where exactly the puck is going to be on the rink, one can be absolutely certain about one thing, and that is that the puck is headed towards the other team’s goal. In a similar sense, the product’s end goal is to suit the needs of the consumer perfectly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consumer is human. The form the product must then take is to suit the form of a human body. If the product is meant to be held, it must fit the hand perfectly. If it is meant to be worn on the ear, then it must fit various ear types. If it is meant to be used over a period of time, then it must use materials that will not strain the user during that period. In terms of the function it performs, it must serve the needs of the human as accurately while also needing as little effort as possible. The final version of the product therefore is possible to define, at least in the abstract.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me illustrate the idea with some examples. Consider the evolution of the USB cable. Type A USB cables required the user guess which way should be facing up before plugging it into a socket. Many users struggled with this and the act of plugging in the USB A cable into a socket was a hit or a miss &lt;em&gt;every time&lt;/em&gt;. Making the cable pluggable into a socket in either orientation therefore was obvious. Therefore that’s what happened in the future iteration of the USB C cable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another issue with the cable was that the sockets it plugged into on the other side was variable. There were the USB A plug, USB B plug, a mini USB plug and even a micro USB plug. You therefore had to have at least one cable of each type in order to be able to connect with various device types that one bought over time, not to mention the proprietary cables that were required by some devices like smart watches. Intuitively one can see that these were too many cables to basically perform the same task. Again, no wonder the USB C cable’s invention. As of the time of writing this article, the USB C cable too has various types, the ones that supply current and the ones that also transfer data. How long do you think that’s going to stay that way?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same principle can be applied to Generative AI tools – do you think specialised prompts are going to be required much longer; computer keyboards – are they more convenient than speech;  or even subscription services – will Adobe get away with charging cancellation charges for their subscription service for much longer?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is easy to answer these questions I suppose. However the problem really lies in defining the intermediate states of the product between it’s current state and the final form. These intermediate states are dictated not by the human being it is meant to serve, but by other constraints such as materials available, the tools, technologies, the people available to build that next version, legal and environmental constraints, the organisational politics, available marketing budgets or even the designer’s inability to understand who the user is. After all, products aren’t designed in a vacuum.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/where-the-puck-is-going-to-be/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/where-the-puck-is-going-to-be/</guid>
        
        <category>design</category>
        
        <category>opinion</category>
        
        
        <category>Ideas</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>My experiments with 3D printing</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;My foray into the world of 3D printing and my learnings and insights so far. This is work in progress and will continue to be edited.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;3d-printing-a-journey-into-a-promising-yet-challenging-field&quot;&gt;3D Printing: A Journey into a Promising, Yet Challenging Field&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in around 2015, I stumbled upon 3D printers during their nascent stage. The potential was clear, but the technology wasn’t quite there yet, and it was relegated to a niche space for tech enthusiasts. As a UX designer, my curiosity was piqued, especially considering the initial buzz surrounding its potential impact on ecommerce and logistics. However, being based in India at the time, affordability, availability of replacement parts, and local support were significant barriers to entry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to 2023, I was blown away by an amazing YouTube video showcasing a user designing and printing all the shelves he needed for his desk, as well as custom SD card holders. This experience resonated with me, reminding me of the excitement I get when visiting a hardware store or a craft shop, imagining the possibilities of creating useful things. I was eager to explore this technology further and get my hands on a 3D printer to discover what I could create.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-right-printer-for-me-balancing-usability-and-performance&quot;&gt;The Right Printer for Me: Balancing Usability and Performance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the 3D printing industry evolved, so did its focus on user experience. Although there are numerous resources available online for fine-tuning printers, many models offer excellent results straight out of the box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of the printing technologies, I narrowed down my choices to Fused Deposition Modelling (FDM) and Vat Polymerisation (VP) printers due to their popularity in the consumer space. VP printing introduced some unique challenges like the need for ventilation and dealing with smells arising from resin. Given that I wanted the printer to remain in my study, I opted for FDM. After thorough research, I selected a printer that offered ease of assembly, maintenance, and accessibility to support. The Bambu Labs X1 and Elegoo Neptune 4 Plus stood out, but ultimately, I went with the Neptune 4 due to its lower cost and absence of proprietary parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;unboxing-and-setting-up-overcoming-challenges-together&quot;&gt;Unboxing and Setting Up: Overcoming Challenges Together&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The delivery took around a month due to pre-ordering, arriving during Christmas holidays, offering ample time for me to delve into learning about 3D printing. The setup was straightforward, but there were some complications like ensuring the correct cables were connected and checking voltage settings on the printer bed. Although these tasks weren’t particularly challenging for a technologically inclined user, they required careful attention and a bit of research to ensure a seamless experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the occasional hurdles, the experience was rewarding, as I was able to build my 3D printer from scratch with all necessary tools supplied. The desktop software that came with the Neptune 4 pleasantly surprised me with pre-installed printable files of a tool stand for the printer!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;designing-the-gap-in-the-ux-of-3d-modelling&quot;&gt;Designing: The Gap in the UX of 3D Modelling&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The design process in 3D modelling is complex and requires a good understanding of visualising 2D cross-sectional shapes to create 3D objects. Sculpting tools like Blender are suitable for creating aesthetically pleasing, non-functional designs, while functional 3D design tools like OnShape offer the best capabilities for product designers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OnShape, a cloud-based platform, boasts responsive and great tools that keep users updated with the latest features. However, the pricing could use improvement to cater to hobbyists and make entry into this space more accessible. Simplifying design tools by incorporating user-friendly features specific to 3D printing would further enhance the overall UX.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;design-marketplaces-tools-and-toys-for-everyone&quot;&gt;Design Marketplaces: Tools and Toys for Everyone&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Websites like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.printables.com&quot;&gt;Printables&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thingiverse.com&quot;&gt;Thingiverse&lt;/a&gt; offer a wealth of user-generated designs, allowing anyone to download and print objects using their 3D printers. This sense of power to create and own is truly exhilarating, enabling users to go from ideation to tangible results in a matter of hours! However, there are challenges like inconsistent quality checks and potential issues with new designers’ designs not being fully optimised for mass consumption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Improving the user experience could involve implementing better quality control measures or allowing experienced designers to review and approve new designs before they are released to the public. Additionally, providing more comprehensive information about dimensions, filament requirements, and print time would significantly improve the overall experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;printing-turning-ideas-into-reality&quot;&gt;Printing: Turning Ideas into Reality&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Printing in 3D isn’t without its challenges – files need to be converted from design formats (usually STL) to Gcode using slicing software like Cura before being printed. This step involves setting various parameters that determine the quality, strength, and speed of the final print. Although these steps are essential, they can be complex for new users. It is also not apparent to users that they may affect the final look of the object with the changes made to some of these settings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Streamlining this process by incorporating it into authoring tools would greatly improve the user experience. Until then, there are numerous resources available online to help users learn the intricacies of 3D printing, allowing them to enjoy the satisfaction of turning their ideas into tangible objects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion-a-promising-future&quot;&gt;Conclusion: A Promising Future&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The potential of 3D printing is immense, and I’m confident that significant improvements will be made to address the unique challenges in this space while keeping user experience at the forefront. Like with all the challenges solved in the 2D printing world, I envision 3D printers becoming an integral part of every household or as more likely, in the neighbourhood print shop. The key to realising this lies in simplifying the design authoring tools and making them accessible to everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;hurdles-and-insights&quot;&gt;Hurdles and Insights&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The plugging in of the cables for the gantry motors still requires some amount of understanding of connectors. This could be further simplified in future versions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The printer plate travels outside the frame of the printer itself which allows a user to make the mistake of placing it too close to a wall and having to learn &lt;em&gt;during printing&lt;/em&gt; that it needs to be moved. This could be explained as well.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Going from 2D to 3D is incredibly difficult and staying in the 3D space from the start would be ideal, but the tools we have today are limited in their ability to express these ideas.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Marketplaces are currently aimed at those that own 3D printers, whereas they should be aimed at the end-users of the products that are available on the sites.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There are two outcomes to the world of 3D printers, they will either become a part of every household of the future as 2D printers today are, or they will become a part of every neighbourhood print shop.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/experiments-with-3d-printing/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/experiments-with-3d-printing/</guid>
        
        <category>3D</category>
        
        <category>design</category>
        
        
        <category>Experiments</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Review of the Rabbit R1</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A detailed review of the newly launched Rabbit R1, exploring its hardware and software design, its strategic position in the market and its potential challenges&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-launch-of-something-new&quot;&gt;The Launch of Something New&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To say that the Rabbit team copied the Steve Jobs keynote would be an understatement! The only thing missing was the Vera Wang turtleneck. It was a black t-shirt instead, but otherwise the same slide style from Apple Keynote with the gradient, the same format for the presentation, the hand gestures, including the “One more thing…” announcement in the end. But OnePlus did this too before, including the turtleneck. While it was thought to be cringe-worthy at the time, the product made up for the lack of originality in presentation. So, let’s not get hung up on style and look at the substance instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;background&quot;&gt;Background&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tech-world has been in pursuit of two things for the past couple of years. The first is an answer to what replaces the smart phone. Depending on who you ask, the smartphone has stayed relatively the same since its debut in 2007. It’s been upgraded in small ways with better screens, cameras and sensors, but otherwise the form-factor has stayed relatively the same since the beginning despite some major flaws in the structure. But it’s been more than 16 years, Steve Jobs isn’t around and everyone’s looking for the smartphone killer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, the success of OpenAI’s Chat GPT has also indicated to everyone how powerful AI assistants can be. The open-source space has also made giant leaps with Llama 2 and Mistral AI models and you can get the same capabilities of ChatGPT and even the interface running on your local computer with relative ease with things like Ollama.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the addition of vision, audio and speech capabilities into AI models, it is now ready to get out of the browser and into the lives of people, being within their own worlds understanding instructions within their own contexts. For this, they may need to leave desktop browser windows and get into the mobile phones instead. But mobile phones are still a reach-into-your-pockets-or-handbag away and that’s not good enough either. People need something even more readily available. Enter Meta RayBan, Humane’s AI Pin, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, these models have so far been hamstrung by their inability to perform actions on behalf of the user. They cannot yet click buttons on screens and other interfaces and the OS architecture and security doesn’t allow an app to interact with the interfaces of other apps as yet, and rightly so. But this also means that we have to duplicate actions and information across apps in order to achieve some goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this backdrop, I think we can evaluate what Rabbit R1 is doing much more accurately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/RabbitR1-2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;hardware-design&quot;&gt;Hardware Design&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems they hired &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/@teenageengin33r&quot;&gt;teenageengineering&lt;/a&gt; (nice name), which seems to have an inclination to create retro-futuristic looking tech products and reminds me of the stuff created by Dieter Rahms’s Braun products. The design is a very cool, lego-inspired shell that houses a great looking touchscreen, a camera on a swivel, a scroll wheel, mics, a slot for USB and SIM cards and a push-button on the right of the product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the touchscreen is a great addition and makes interacting with apps, seeing information delivery much faster, answering questions and such much, much faster than audio based delivery which the AI Pin by Humane chose to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The camera on a swivel seems like a good idea as the R1 can potentially scan the environment to find what a user may be referring to in their instructions. But the plastic above the camera will not let the device be held in an angle less than about 45 degrees and the user will need to position the device almost vertically like they do smartphones for the camera to be able to see. This is weird, so I am not sure why this choice was made either. Why not just position the camera on the very edge without the top plastic part causing an obstruction?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/RabbitR1-3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m also not able to rationalise the use of the analog scroll wheel. Is it meant to help make choices within the touch screen? Doesn’t seem likely as its potentially faster to use your finger to scroll on the touchscreen. Is it meant to manually position the camera? If that’s the case, positioning it to the right of the camera would have been better. Is it meant to make scrolling on the touchscreen a single-handed operation? If I was holding it in my left hand, using my index finger to scroll the screen instead of my thumb on the screen &lt;em&gt;may&lt;/em&gt; be easier, but I’ll probably still have to make button selections and for that I may be hitting the push-button. This seems like learned behaviour but the only explanation I can come up with given my limited understanding. But if you hold this device in you right hand, you can’t explain the position of the scroll wheel at all! You can’t scroll with the thumb which is holding the side of the device and you can’t use your left hand to use the scroll wheel as you’ll block your view of the screen. So, why then?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I didn’t see any ways for the product to be put onto a jacket or shirt and the placement of the screen and the push-button seems to indicate that the R1 is meant to be carried in a pocket and pulled out when it needs to be used. This is a big red flag for me. An AI companion needs to be always available within the context of the user’s physical space in order to understand instructions better (and to keep the instructions simpler). If it needs to be pulled out of a pocket or more likely from a bag as the smartphone will be in the pocket, this will not be as easily accessible. The AI Pin did better in this regard by being always accessible from the t-shirt or jacket where it is clamped. The Meta RayBan was another good attempt at this but given that they are sunglasses, the ability to wear them all the time is nearly impossible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;software-design&quot;&gt;Software Design&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jesse Lyu, the founder and CEO begins his keynote by actually recognising one of the most fundamental issues with the way smartphones are designed. This is an extremely deep insight and I’m so glad someone on such a large stage was able to express this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the early days of the smartphone, Apple proudly used the line, “There’s an app for that” in their marketing to highlight how many apps there were in the App Store. You see, in their view, there was an app that could achieve any task that you wanted to do. But the mental model of a person who wants to perform a specific task needs to then make a choice in their minds of the app that would enable to do it and then open that app and then make the right choices in the interfaces in order to achieve that task. If you’ve got more than one app that could help you do that task, there’s some time spent in your mind making a choice between them. And if you have a task that needs more than one task to be achieved, you’ve just made the choices even more complex. Given that most people have about 90 different apps on their phones on average, this isn’t a small matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You also need to have downloaded these app ahead of time in anticipation of a need for it in the future. But that’s another story altogether.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is also third-generation thinking where you have to think of the objective you need to achieve and then break it down into the steps required in order for the computer to help you achieve it. Contrast that with the fourth-generation thinking which simply needs the user to clearly express the goal and the computer then breaks down the tasks into the atomic bits, figures out the best tools to use to solve the problem and solves it. This was science fiction before the advent of AI. This is reality today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s also the duplication of data and instructions between the apps to contend with. For example, travelling somewhere on a vacation requires an app for flight bookings, an app for hotel bookings, an app to book a ride and another to research the highlights of the destination. Each of them will ask you for your name, dates, times and locations, your companions, your preferences, over and over again. And that’s not even considering the fact that you need to register with each app too!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a problem today and Jesse and company used this idea as the foundation to build their solution to combat this problem. Kudos to them to being able to figure out a way around with their Rabbit Hole interface, even though it doesn’t yet completely solve &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; the problems as yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s much more to say about the software, the interfaces and the UI design which are all brilliant, but table-stakes for a game this big. The fact that they understood the above point and also broke through the 500ms (while not yet hitting the Doherty Threshold) makes the device feel really responsive is just amazing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;business-design&quot;&gt;Business Design&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that the product was launched at $199 is simply a master stroke. A device that purports to be an AI Companion is really only that useful today and the price-point is perfect. But how could they not have a recurring monthly fee? They have to have servers running in the background to serve the needs of the users. How do they expect to fund this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me, this is where the Rabbit Hole comes in. I think the apps need to pay to be listed there. Maybe not initially, but eventually. They also may have a local model running on the device that handles the majority of the daily queries and only passing along the complex ones to the server a la &lt;a href=&quot;https://mistral.ai/news/mixtral-of-experts/&quot;&gt;Mixtral of Experts&lt;/a&gt;. This would keep their costs low too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a possibility where they are going to be the benefactors of a model that understands the physical world of the user better. This is green-field at the moment and they are going to be one of the first to occupy this space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this is me just conjecturing and the answer may be far simpler and the operational costs may just be borne through VC funding until they hit some kind of a threshold. Or maybe it has to do with advertising a. k. a. “recommendations” that the agent provides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The R1 is intriguing and addresses some key concerns of mobile computing. However, several challenges persist. While Rabbit R1 excels in software, the hardware design falls short of being an effective AI companion. A smart watch with a camera still remains the form factor to beat. Given these shortcomings, I predict limited usage and abandonment by most users within a few months unless these improvements are implemented by the time they start shipping in March.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With regards to competition, this concept could easily be replicated by smartphone manufacturers. If they cannot produce it independently, an acquisition could be on the cards, which may be the anticipated endgame anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For any AI companion the major obstacle remains payments. The demo didn’t quite show how the many payments that were alluded to be taking place actually happened and I’m curious to see how this bit works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I don’t personally wish to purchase this product due to the aforementioned issues and deficiencies, I still regard it as a ‘directional innovation’ that pushes the industry in the proper direction. There will be numerous iterations before the ideal form factor for the product is realized, as well as the perfect business models for the companies backing them. Consequently, I intend to keep a close eye on Jesse and his team to see if they adapt and iterate as I anticipate they will.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/rabbit-r1-review/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/rabbit-r1-review/</guid>
        
        <category>design</category>
        
        <category>technology</category>
        
        <category>hardware</category>
        
        
        <category>Reviews</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Design review of the AI Pin by Humane</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As a product designer, I analysed Humane’s first product, the AI Pin, and identified several critical challenges that need to be addressed. While the product’s primary purpose of replacing mobile phones is laudable, it faces significant obstacles. Firstly, the device needs to offer a 10X better value proposition than the mobile phone to convince users to switch. However, this proved difficult as the AI Pin struggled to deliver on this promise, particularly in terms of call and message functionality, social media, calendar management, navigation, photography, entertainment, running apps, and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the voice-based input/output and low-resolution screen limit the device’s usefulness compared to a high-resolution touchscreen display. Additionally, the need for a tap activation can be slow and cumbersome, hindering the AI assistant’s utility. Demonstrations showed that the AI assistant takes time to retrieve information and respond, leading to frustration in daily usage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/HumaneAIPin.jpeg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To improve the product, I would ask the following questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why create a phone replacement as the first version of the product? It would have been more effective to demonstrate the usefulness of an always-available AI assistant, as Meta RayBan did.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why use tap as a wake gesture when hot keywords or head turns towards the device could be faster and more hands-free?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What were the reasons for not pursuing a smartwatch with video capabilities? A watch offers familiar activation gestures like raising to wake, and provides a screen for information delivery and private touch inputs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While many have criticised this project, upon closer examination, it appears that the product was rushed to market rather than be the example of the company’s vision. However, there is still hope for Humane as they continue to innovate. A truly effective always-available AI assistant has the potential to improve various aspects of life, and I await their future developments with interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to go into uncharted waters, and one must admire them for trying.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 28 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/review-of-humane-ai-pin/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/review-of-humane-ai-pin/</guid>
        
        <category>design</category>
        
        <category>hardware</category>
        
        
        <category>Reviews</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Is there room for another dating app?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Examining whether there’s an actual need missing or a packaging problem&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-need&quot;&gt;The Need&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meeting the person that is now my wife had been quite a challenge. I probably have been helped by friends, family and work colleagues and when that didn’t work, I even joined a singles group, signed up online on matrimonial sites and even dating apps. I finally met my wife on a dating app called OkCupid. To say that this field of allowing people to find each other is dear to me would be an understatement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been happily married for a while now. I have several single friends my age and while a few of them want to find someone and get married eventually, some are choosing to stay single and are quite content doing so. However they would still like companionship and would like to meet people that are similarly inclined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a recent conversation with four twenty-something user experience designers, I asked about dating apps and whether they are serving the needs of people their age group. But surprisingly the complaints were the same as for those that belong to the older group I spoke of above. All of them said they had issues meeting people and that no dating app was serving them well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a broader societal level India has always been thought of as a nation with very traditional values and therefore the population had a majority of married people. But this trend is changing. People are getting married later in life if at all and many are also choosing to stay single, not seeing getting married and having kids as the final goal. Divorce laws in India are also complicated to say the least and this may be a contributing factor to people choosing to stay single.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/Pencil-sketch-of-a-happy-couple-sitting-across-each-other-at-a-sidewalk-cafe-in-a-European-city-with-2.jpeg.webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-problems&quot;&gt;The Problems&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my research, I’ve funnily had absolutely no trouble getting people to tell me about the issues they’ve faced while using dating apps. It usually ends up becoming an hour-long conversation and everyone wants to explain their individual journeys and issues that they’ve run into. In a lot of ways they want to vent their frustration and when someone like me comes along and asks what the issues are, it’s like opening the flood gates to a dam. But I feel their pain as I’ve been there myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To whit, the issues they presented for dating were as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Men find it harder to meet women as the percentage of men on dating platforms is much higher. This may be because it’s traditionally been uncommon for women to put their profiles online.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is not easy to convert an online encounter into a physical meeting due to concerns regarding security. They typically want to be very sure of the person before they meet.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People prefer to meet others in real life rather than online as that is a more authentic way to find someone.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Creating a good profile is key and people request others who have found success to create their profiles. But this inadvertently also adds to the catfishing concern as the profiles may not be authentic at all.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People don’t always know that the person they are meeting online are verified in any way and this adds to security concerns.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dating apps that require women to initiate the connection may be adding a hurdle to introverted women. They may prefer to be approached instead. But this an an all-or-nothing kind of offering on such platforms.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ghosting is a big concern as people may be spending inordinate amounts of time trying to build a relationship with someone they met online whereas the other person may be not be interested at all but doesn’t know how to end this.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The online medium is skewed towards good-looking people. The fact is that most platforms offer huge databases of people and it’s practically impossible to sift through all without being extremely quick to judge either based on photos or based on scanning of profiles very quickly.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There are several scams that have occurred based on people meeting each other online in India. Scams involve extortion, confidence scams, honey traps and lots of other such issues that make this kind of meeting very dubious.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some things that could be solved through better employment of technology. But there are a lot of things that can be solved in the real-world realm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/Pencil-sketch-of-a-happy-group-of-friends-at-a-sidewalk-cafe-in-a-European-city-with-sharp-focus-on-.jpeg.webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;room-for-another&quot;&gt;Room for Another&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the passage of time, it’s a good idea to evaluate old decisions over again. While I had previously thought that this market is overcrowded and that there is dating-app-fatigue that has set in, I think the advent of AI has made it possible to evaluate this once again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, I am very aware that platforms like e-harmony and OKCupid, and lots of others, have indeed marketed based on this idea. However, I don’t think they had the tools we have today to make that claim in earnest. Besides, the one flaw in their thinking was that they were only able to go so far as making a recommendation of who they would match with; they were never able to evaluate whether they had made the right prediction because they had no mechanism to receive such feedback. If they didn’t get any feedback, it definitely didn’t help make future recommendations any better either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If one were to venture into this field, this is a key aspect that I would evaluate: did they have good recommendation engines that not only had recommendations but also had feedback loops to make future recommendations better?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/Pencil-sketch-of-two-people-in-business-suits-having-coffee-at-a-sidewalk-cafe-in-a-European-city-h.jpeg.webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-business-case&quot;&gt;The Business Case&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my quick study of this field I’ve come to the conclusion that the demand is off-the-charts. No platform has solved this problem as yet, so there’s definitely room for another entrant. There is no dearth of money as people are willing to pay out of money in order to meet the right person. So it can definitely be a profitable venture. But the solution has to be packaged correctly and the right promises need to be made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-goal&quot;&gt;The Goal&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First and foremost it is important to set the right goals for a platform. Is it meant to result in a date, is it meant to result in a relationship, is it meant to result in a marriage or is it simply to develop companionship in this changing world. I think apps and platforms that promise finding the person to get married to are obviously overselling what they are capable of. I’d go so far as to say that even if they promise a great date. It takes a lot more to make a date memorable than the matching of characteristics in databases. I’d love to see an app that promises that the user would meet good people and that’s it, because that’s a promise that can be kept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;target-audience&quot;&gt;Target Audience&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While some people may be looking at getting married, some may simply be looking for companionship or even to meet other singles because the conversations with their married friends maybe something they can’t relate with anymore. I think it would be prudent to simply focus on the people looking to make friends. If something more were to develop from this, that’s just the cherry on top and not the baseline expectation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may also therefore not be an age or gender-related qualification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;packaging&quot;&gt;Packaging&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my mind, the following are the core areas to keep in mind when designing a solution:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-security&quot;&gt;1. Security&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above, we need to make security the main focus area. We need to find ways to make sure that people feel confident when participating on a platform. Vetted profiles, membership through recommendations, attracting people through the right channels, etc. are some of the things that we can do to make sure of this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-authenticity&quot;&gt;2. Authenticity&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While making an effort to make all the profiles on the platform look good, the authenticity of the profile must not be lost. There is a fine balance here that must be found. Maybe the profile is written by those trained in it, but there could also be a video that the user records of themselves saying things that should be added with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-matching&quot;&gt;3. Matching&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the fundamental level this is a matching problem. There is a lot of noise to sift through to find good information and characteristics to match people against. People often lie about themselves in order to appear a certain way and no questionnaire can overcome this hurdle. Or, they may not express what they want for fear of being judged for it. Yet again, they may simply not know what they want. All of this makes the matching problem more difficult for any system, but not for machine learning systems. Building a good matching engine that powers all of this is therefore the most important task. And for this, we need as many signals and feedback as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-efficiency&quot;&gt;4. Efficiency&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is one of the most ignored metrics within this field. People spend inordinate amounts of time trying to find the right person that they would like to be with. This increases the fatigue that they face and makes a lot of people give up in the middle of the process. Any new system that is built should definitely consider making this entire process more efficient. The system should try to match a person with a group of people that they share common ground with. The individual they meet within that group that they connect with is almost unnecessary to focus on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pricing&quot;&gt;Pricing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pricing will obviously play a key role here. Pricing can be used to create an elite group that keeps the non-serious participants out, but too high a price and it will become elitist and exclusionary. People should also not be paying for individual participation, but rather for a few different events together so that they interact repeatedly as that is key to the success of this program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/Pencil-sketch-of-a-happy-group-of-friends-at-a-sidewalk-cafe-in-a-European-city-highly-detailed-and.jpeg.webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The world is yearning for deeper connections. With the power of technology at our fingertips, it’s time to harness it and create platforms that truly bring people together. We must seize this opportunity to build communities, foster companionship, and combat the growing loneliness in our society. It’s time to reimagine dating platforms as platforms that serve this need, where the focus is on meeting good people and forming meaningful connections. Let’s embrace the advancements in AI and recommendation engines to make this vision a reality. We have the tools, the potential, and the responsibility to improve the human connection. It’s time to take action and create a platform that truly changes lives. It must be attempted because it is important to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/is-there-room-for-another-dating-app/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/is-there-room-for-another-dating-app/</guid>
        
        <category>opinion</category>
        
        <category>society</category>
        
        
        <category>Ideas</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Generative AI Art Experiments</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Artificial Intelligence (AI) based design tools have captivated our collective imagination in the field of design. Here are my experiments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Artificial Intelligence (AI) based design tools have captivated our collective imagination in the field of design. Being able to imagine something and bring it to life in the form of an image or video is a tempting prospect. While one part of the design world lamented the fact that these tools may replace our roles, I belong to the small minority that looks at these new technologies with the hope that it would lead to better design. I could after all never call myself a designer if I had never run into Photoshop all those years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I dove in head-first into figuring out what this new frontier holds for us. This is an on-going experiment and I am just documenting my learnings as I go along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If not for Photoshop, I may have never become a designer&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-did-i-expect&quot;&gt;What did I expect?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I started exploring this simply out of curiosity, it later was also a business decision as I anticipated that it would help my small team do more. After all we were about to launch a second product at work and I had to find ways to  sustain all of it with the current team size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, I started by trying to find answers to the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What are the tools that are available?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What’s the learning curve to use these technologies?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How much control do I have over the output?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How much post-processing is required?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Can they produce consistent quality and style over a period of time?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Are the technologies mature enough for everyday use?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;october-2022-ai-based-art-nfts&quot;&gt;October 2022: AI based art NFTs&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had heard of AI generated art and was amazed by what I saw in some videos but I had no idea how this was done or how. I happened to run into NFT’s on Rarible at that time and saw this collection of AI based images that someone had made. I was just so amazed with its accuracy that I ended up buying a few of them simply in the hope that I was supporting someone who was working on this and possibly getting flack for not being a true artist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;learnings-from-this-phase&quot;&gt;Learnings from this phase:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AI art is dividing the world into the group that thinks this is art and the group that thinks it isn’t&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;No one expected AI would set its sights on the creative fields first.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;display: table;&quot;&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;display: table-row;&quot;&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;display: table-cell;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/GenerativeAIArt-2.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Image 1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;display: table-cell;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/GenerativeAIArt-3.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Image 2&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;february-2023-midjourney&quot;&gt;February 2023: MidJourney&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran into MidJourney back in late 2022 through a colleague who was using it to create some artwork that I was quite impressed with. I thought to try it out but the version that existed at the time was just not that great with the simple “prompts” I was able to provide it. It took too many tries and much too long to generate something just remotely close to what I wanted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw others developing images that looked a lot better and saw what they had prompted MJ in order to produce it. I copied one of them that had produced a very cool image of a cat to produce an image of a dog. My dog image had three eyes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My attempts at producing human portraits didn’t fare much better. All of them had messed up hands or too many fingers for some reason. I was producing Dali-esque images without intending to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I walked away from a two hour session kind of impressed, but feeling that the tech wasn’t there yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;learnings-from-this-phase-1&quot;&gt;Learnings from this phase:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The learning curve was too great as I would never be able to understand all the words and prompts and styles and exclusions if I had to type all of this out&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The interface (Discord) was absolutely not the one that I could imagine using to produce images. It was a terrible fit and since I was in a public channel typing out my requests, I felt like I was being watched while I fumbled around trying to produce the output I wanted.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tech wasn’t there yet, but I saw potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;march-2023-midjourney-v5&quot;&gt;March 2023: MidJourney V5&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MJ V5 launched this month and I got really interested. This was a big update and they got a whole lot of changes in. They got the hands right, they got faces right, the quality of images was just amazing and the initially released with the Zoom Out feature that essentially imagined the parts of the frame that wasn’t there before and gave images this depth and drama that didn’t exist before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pace of smaller updates thereon has just been incredible and it was time for my team to start experimenting with it. As we had been working on building an NFT collection for use with the main product as rewards, this ability to generate a lot of graphics in a short period of time was important. The challenge was being able to get MJ5 to output the kinds of images that we had been producing until now with Blender.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The alternative was to produce a new style that worked with MJ5 but that also meant updating all the graphical properties that the company had, including the website, marketing collateral, transactional content and other assets such as NFTs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the team started to work with this and try and achieve our existing styles of artwork with the new tools. However this yielded pretty bad results. There was still a lot of manual effort required to bring the artwork to the same style. So we abandoned this approach and started pursuing the second strategy and came up with a new direction altogether.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;learnings-from-this-phase-2&quot;&gt;Learnings from this phase:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The tooling was still not good enough for a designer. It seemed like you can only do a full-image edit and not something specific within it. For that you’d still need tools like Photoshop. Photoshop’s generative fill provides much more control.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Knowing that we can produce the required graphics with such ease suddenly allowed us think about doing sweeping changes that we would never think about doing before. We’re now able to think about updating a website in preparation for a launch event.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I feel that we’re still at a stage where you can still tell when artwork has been produced by AI. It’s just “too polished” and accurate. Not sure what this means as yet, but I’m trying to understand it more.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stable Diffusion came onto my radar as a platform that provides us more control within the AI generative tools space. So I started exploring that next.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;scribe-characters-created-with-blender&quot;&gt;‘SCRIBE’ CHARACTERS CREATED WITH BLENDER&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;display: table;&quot;&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;display: table-row;&quot;&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;display: table-cell;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/GenerativeAIArt-4.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Image 1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;display: table-cell;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/GenerativeAIArt-5.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Image 2&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;display: table-cell;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/GenerativeAIArt-6.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Image 3&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;scribe-characters-created-with-midjourney-50&quot;&gt;‘SCRIBE’ CHARACTERS CREATED WITH MIDJOURNEY 5.0&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;display: table;&quot;&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;display: table-row;&quot;&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;display: table-cell;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/GenerativeAIArt-7.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Image 1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;display: table-cell;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/GenerativeAIArt-8.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Image 2&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;display: table-cell;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/GenerativeAIArt-9.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Image 3&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/generative-ai-art-experiments/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/generative-ai-art-experiments/</guid>
        
        <category>technology</category>
        
        <category>art</category>
        
        
        <category>Experiments</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Better tools should be better employed</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;When you have access to tools that provide you unlimited capability, how should these tools be used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the age of AI, the only limitation to creating things is our ability to imagine them. While AI tools allow for new possibilities, there is a real growing concern that our ability to imagine itself may be eviscerated. But uniquely to our time, there are dire consequences to using &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; not using the technologies. The only way forward is to pay attention to where we employ these tools and where we don’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Design is about changing and managing perceptions and ideas about the world we live in. It’s powerful because when employed well, it works wonders as a way of wielding influence. This influence can broaden our horizons, make us aware of our hidden biases and even train good behaviour. Or, on the other hand, it can block progress and foster addictive and unhealthy behaviours such as providing positive reinforcement when we buy stuff we don’t need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/BetterTools-2.webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;two-stories&quot;&gt;Two Stories&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently watched this wonderful video by Dami Lee where she analysed the fantastic amount of detail that the people at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ghibli.jp/&quot;&gt;Studio Ghibli&lt;/a&gt; went into while creating some of the award-winning animated movies that they are known for. Since Dami Lee is an architect, she analysed the movies from that perspective and highlighted how thoughtfully the buildings were detailed, including the details of lobbies, the rooms themselves, and even what the long passageways mean in terms of the Japanese culture they represent. She’s fascinated that the studio is able to be this observant and dives in to find out what about their design process makes this possible. And this, to me, in my current role as the head of a design team, was what I found most interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the video, there are clips of interviews with one of the founders &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hayao_Miyazaki&quot;&gt;Hayao Miyazaki&lt;/a&gt; where he states that they force everyone to animate things in the traditional way “by hand” even though this is far more painstaking and tedious. He says that this, in fact, is the reason the studio has been able to be as observant as they have been. He insists that this is the case and goes on to berate anyone that wants to use technology or find a faster way to do things. He famously has said, “Anyone that eats instant ramen three times a day cannot be an animator,” further emphasising the idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Anyone that eats instant Ramen three times a day cannot be an animator”
– Hayao Miyazaki, Co-Founder, Studio Ghibli&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a completely different part of the world, a friend of mine had developed an appreciation for calligraphy and had begun dabbling with it. He showed me the various pages where he had written the same letter over and over again. Being extremely observant he had observed how he had to move his hand in order to achieve the right shape of the stroke and paid attention to how the ink flowed on the paper. He had even crafted the right kind of pens and nibs to be able to do this easily. But his biggest learning was that the effort involved in the art actually made him think many times about what it is that he wanted to convey. It had to be something important as the very act of embellishing the letters took a lot of time and effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He went on to remark at the virtues of the art of letter writing of the ages past that our grandparents were very familiar with. He saw that there was something beautiful in the effort one put not only into the writing of the letters, but also the pasting, stamping, walking the letter over to the nearby postbox that somehow conveyed to the recipient and made them so happy or at least important for being the beneficiary of such effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems there was something to the deliberation involved and the lack of speed, that made for greater appreciation. And this got me thinking about the design process I use in my daily work as a user experience designer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/BetterTools-3.webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-better-ux-design-process&quot;&gt;A Better UX Design Process&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;User Experience Design as a field gained foothold with the advent of computers and the invention of the Graphical User Interface. It’s been a digital pursuit since it’s inception and as such technology has been used to improve every aspect of the process, right from research, wire-framing, visual design, implementation and testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those unfamiliar with this field, the main job of a UX designer is to visualise how an application would look and feel like before it has been developed by programmers, much like an architect would render drawings of a building on paper before the building gets built. The task therefore is of communication to all the stakeholders. The hope is that any fixes that are required are done at the design stage when it is cheaper rather than at the development stage when it is definitely much more expensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even a considerably simple application requires more than fifty screens to be designed if every scenario anticipated while using it needs to be thought through. For example, how does a user login, how do they set their preferences, how do they communicate with support personnel, how do they bring their friends onto the app, and so on. When you factor in the additional operating systems and the various devices and screen sizes that the application should work on, you can easily understand how many screens need to be developed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine if something that appears on all the screens needs to be changed (which happens more frequently than one thinks), a designer will have to manually locate the said element in each of the screens and replace them. Using Photoshop, Illustrator or Fireworks, which were tools we used to use to design these screens, this took hours or even days of mind-numbing effort and designers hated doing this. They would do anything to avoid rework, including pushing back on any change requests, pushing the task to the developers to handle at the time of development or even just changing the process to seek inputs and feedback on just key screens before all the associated screens in the process are completely developed which is not really the best way to do this as the stakeholders are evaluating based on insufficient information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, we have much better tools like Figma which make these changes across hundreds of screens in a matter of seconds. This one ability has allowed us to create much better designs, seek feedback after a lot of screens covering a lot of scenarios are actually developed improving the quality of the output immensely. From my vantage point, it’s clearly evident that this kind of technology has been great for the industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in this mad rush to achieve outputs faster, the same tools also offers the ability for designers to use templates to speed up the work even further. There are AI design tools that are being created that would create entire workflows and in some cases even apps with a single prompt. Like painters of canvasses, UX designers have also got to pay attention to every pixel that they place on the screen. Everything is deliberated upon and nothing happens by accident which is why the outputs are meaningful. This part of the process should remain slow for a reason. If technology is used to reduce the deliberation in an effort to ease this part of the process, the outputs of such processes will undoubtedly be mediocre.
___&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/BetterTools-4.webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;counter-arguments&quot;&gt;Counter Arguments&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some cases, “mediocre” may be a desirable step up. For example, A business owner for instance may simply want to test out an idea for an app without the kinds of expenses involved in the design and development of a custom-built application. But there’s a risk here. A friend of mine advised me about which bicycle to buy this way, “Don’t get a basic bike if you intend to get into this sport. You won’t like the bike and you’ll end up rejecting the sport instead.” I think there’s a lot of truth in that statement and I’d like to provide the same warning to the business owner who may be tempted to use this route. Testing out a good idea using mediocre ways to get you to the output is actually not testing out the idea at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A UX designer also may be tempted to use these tools to define a baseline for the app that they want to develop. These tools may still serve a purpose, but fixing a bad output is probably harder than creating the right output from scratch. There’s also the possibility that not every aspect of the output is examined as well as when creating the output in the first place. Would you want your app to go out to developers with these flaws still in it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Don’t get a basic bike if you intend to get into this sport. You won’t like the bike and you’ll end up rejecting the sport instead.”
– Rohan Kini, Bums on the Saddle&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think technology is a tool like any other and can be beneficial or detrimental depending on how we use it. It will always lure us with its promise of speed, scale, spread, smarts and asynchrony. While it can improve our lives, indiscriminate employment of it will only result in poor outputs. We must be vigilant about what we employ these tools for. Reduction of effort is a great reason to use technology, but if it can impede our thoughtfulness, it is probably a bad use of it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/better-tools-should-be-better-employed/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/better-tools-should-be-better-employed/</guid>
        
        <category>ux</category>
        
        <category>opinion</category>
        
        
        <category>Ideas</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Eight Essential Rules for Mastering Ethical UX Design</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Reflecting on the work of many others and my own work within the field, I have distilled the following rules to act as a guide&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While UX design is a relatively young field, its importance in a product’s success cannot be overstated. Its impact on the world today is clear, but sadly its ability to effect positive change is coupled with its ability to inflict harm. As with anything that has such powerful duality, a code of ethics is necessary to act as a lodestone to guide those venturing into this field in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reflecting on the work of many others and my own work within the field, I have distilled the following rules that should act as a guide:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;rule-1-your-foremost-duty-is-to-help-your-client-succeed&quot;&gt;Rule #1: Your foremost duty is to help your client succeed&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started my design career at Adobe Systems and then went on to build my own UX design agency. My ideas regarding this subject have evolved from “The designer’s job is to advocate for the user within a company” to “The designer is the servant of two masters and needs to figure out how to balance the two”, and finally to understanding that a company simply cannot have interests in opposition to those of its customers for any reasonable length of time, as customers are not naive people waiting to be tricked and will just switch to the nearest substitute. So, it’s enough to simply take the interest of your client — their true long-term interest — and design for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;rule-2-your-task-is-to-help-a-user-simply-navigate-a-complex-world&quot;&gt;Rule #2: Your task is to help a user simply navigate a complex world&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Software is usually employed by a user for the completion of reasonably complicated tasks. Depending on the user, they may be unfamiliar with how to use the software, use the hardware, understand how technology functions, or even have physical limitations such as not being able to see small fonts clearly. Our job as designers is to help them navigate the technology in such a way that it is very simple for them to achieve their tasks. We may need to help them understand the decisions they need to make better, they may need settings that make interfaces more visible, they may rely on the software to make certain choices for them, etc. The better we understand our users, the better we can serve them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;rule-3-dont-treat-the-user-like-a-commodity&quot;&gt;Rule #3: Don’t treat the user like a commodity&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The anonymity one has on the internet is a double-edged sword. While it encourages free speech and discourse, it allows people to behave worse online than they would in real life. In the commercial world, this extends to thinking of users of a product in the abstract, reducing them to single dimensions as pockets that need to be picked, resources meant to be exploited, rats to be subjected to dopamine experiments, or as commodities meant to be traded. This is not good for the company in the long run (a la rule #1), but people attempt to do it anyway. Designers can play a big role in breaking these mindsets and making product managers or companies look at the long-term welfare of their users and, consequently, their own companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;rule-4-your-counsel-is-as-important-as-your-labour&quot;&gt;Rule #4: Your counsel is as important as your labour&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Far too often, we measure our work by the effort we put in or the number of screens and experiences we produce. But I’ve always felt that they hire you for your skills in the early part of your career, and when you’ve gained more experience, they &lt;a href=&quot;https://re/&quot;&gt;h&lt;/a&gt;ire you for your opinions . When we’re designing something, we’re deeply considering a specific point, making decisions based on them and learning from their outcomes. It is this distillation of experience that is more important to a client than our labour. They shouldn’t have to spend new money to learn old lessons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;rule-5-a-designer-must-respect-cultures-genders-physical-abilities-political-leanings-and-privacy-preferences-and-must-design-to-enhance-all-of-them&quot;&gt;Rule #5: A designer must respect cultures, genders, physical abilities, political leanings and privacy preferences and must design to enhance all of them&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much too often we think only through the lens of our biases and it’s all too easy to exclude certain people or groups from our thinking. I am myself guilty of not accommodating people with poor eyesight and early on in my life as a designer, I’d design applications with small fonts because they made the interfaces so cool. But this meant I’d ostracise a large group of people that found it hard to read the small fonts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An even more subtle example is the frustration that one feels while using tools like Google Docs or Microsoft Word or many other software, where they have to change the locale setting &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; time they create a new document as it usually defaults to ‘US English’ even if you’ve previously gone and set this to ‘Indian English’, ‘UK English’ or ‘Australian English’, or any of the many other dialects. I’ve seen people delivering food in India wearing t-shirts that say “Hunger Savior” instead of “Hunger Saviour” because someone forgot to change the locale setting while writing the copy for that t-shirt ! But there are even worse examples I have seen websites that use “Father’s Name” as a label for a field where “Parent’s Name” would have been more appropriate. Should someone really pick the option that says “childless”, even if they &lt;em&gt;chose&lt;/em&gt; not to have children and wouldn’t choosing “0” against children not be a more neutral choice! But here’s something that probably affects a lot more people — the methods of proving that you’re a human by typing in the English text displayed in a box. The majority of the world &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;doesn’t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; speak English natively!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it may be challenging to cater to every user’s unique preferences, being aware of these potential biases is the first step in creating more inclusive designs. By being open to feedback from users and making an effort to understand their perspectives, designers can work towards creating applications and products that are welcoming and accommodating for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;rule-6-protect-the-privacy-of-your-users&quot;&gt;Rule #6: Protect the privacy of your users&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the digital age, privacy has become a vital concern for users as their personal information is often at risk of being exploited by powerful entities. Although many people understand the importance of privacy, not everyone is aware of its implications on their own lives or how to select platforms that prioritize this aspect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, it falls upon product designers to make critical decisions on behalf of their users, ensuring that privacy is protected throughout their designs. By being conscious of potential privacy risks and implementing robust security measures, designers can help safeguard users’ personal information and maintain their trust in the products and platforms they use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anne Cavoukian, the Information and Privacy officer of Ontario, proposed a set of seven foundational principles to protect the users of most information systems called “Privacy by Design” (PbD). The core idea is to address privacy concerns from the beginning, instead of adding privacy measures as an afterthought. PbD comprises seven foundational principles:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Proactive not Reactive; Preventative not Remedial: Privacy by Design emphasises anticipating and preventing privacy invasions before they happen, rather than waiting for breaches to occur and then taking remedial action.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Privacy as the Default Setting: Privacy should be built into systems and services by default, so users don’t have to take any action to protect their privacy. This means that personal data should be automatically protected without requiring any user intervention.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Privacy Embedded into Design: Privacy should be an integral part of the design and architecture of IT systems and business practices. This ensures that privacy is not treated as an add-on but is a core component of the system or service.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Full Functionality — Positive-Sum, not Zero-Sum: PbD advocates for a “win-win” approach where both privacy and functionality are achieved, without compromising either. It rejects the idea that privacy must be sacrificed for security or other objectives.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;End-to-End Security — Lifecycle Protection: Privacy by Design emphasises the need for strong security measures throughout the entire data lifecycle — from collection to use, storage, and eventual disposal. This involves implementing robust access controls, encryption, and other security techniques.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Visibility and Transparency: PbD emphasises being open and transparent about privacy practices, allowing users and other stakeholders to verify that privacy measures are in place and functioning as intended. This fosters trust and confidence in the system or service.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Respect for User Privacy: Privacy by Design puts users at the centre, giving them control over their personal data and making it easy for them to exercise their privacy rights. This includes mechanisms for obtaining consent, providing access to personal information, and allowing users to correct or delete their data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make applications respect users’ privacy, follow these steps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Conduct a privacy impact assessment at the beginning of the project to identify potential privacy risks and develop strategies to address them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Design the application with privacy in mind, incorporating the Privacy by Design principles from the start.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Collect only the minimum necessary personal data and anonymise or pseudonymise data where possible.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Implement strong access controls and encryption to protect personal data in transit and at rest.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Establish clear and transparent privacy policies, making them easily accessible to users.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Offer users options to manage their privacy settings, giving them control over their personal data.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Regularly review and update privacy practices, staying informed of changes in regulations and industry best practices.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;rule-7-find-every-opportunity-to-reduce-the-carbon-footprint&quot;&gt;Rule #7: Find every opportunity to reduce the carbon footprint&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When e-commerce companies first launched in India, every step from the moment a user completed payment on a website to the final delivery of the product to the user’s home was new and untested. One such process was the packaging method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It appears that packaging and shipping standards from another country were adopted, with every product arriving in bubble wrap and oversized boxes, regardless of the contents. However, it is well-known that India is averse to waste, be it food on a plate or in business, nothing is allowed to go to waste. When oversized boxes started appearing at people’s doorsteps for items as small as lipstick, deodorant, or a bar of soap, people began to complain!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This led to someone in the logistics department reevaluating the situation and adapting the Standard Operating Procedures (SOPs) to suit waste-intolerant Indian conditions. Packaging underwent a rapid transformation across all e-commerce players: boxes were replaced by envelopes when possible, clothes were wrapped in brown paper, the number of shipments decreased, and items were grouped. Other changes included shipping items to a neighbourhood store for customer pick-up and making numerous other adjustments in a short time. Encouraging a company to adopt environmentally-friendly practices is challenging, but e-commerce companies embraced these strategies because they aligned with their interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This prompted me to think about design interventions that could benefit the company, customer, and environment. A few ideas immediately came to mind that e-commerce companies could implement:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Allow users to specify their preferred packaging for the products they order.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Let users indicate if they need their items urgently or are willing to wait for grouped deliveries with others in the area, enabling the packaging department to avoid always defaulting to the “safest” option.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Food delivery companies can improve the value-per-mile metric for their delivery personnel by allowing them to collect used plastic containers from customers, streamlining recycling efforts.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Offer subscription options for frequently ordered products, optimising delivery routes and making them more predictable.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Allow users to inform product manufacturers of their preference for eco-friendly alternatives, which could encourage manufacturers to develop such options if there is sufficient demand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are five ideas with me spending a few hours thinking about the problem. Imagine the possibilities if designers everywhere also focussed on this problem. And that’s the main call to action in this rule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;rule-8-design-for-delight-not-for-addiction&quot;&gt;Rule #8: Design for delight, not for addiction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Design is an incredibly powerful tool that can help achieve any goal. There have been numerous shows and documentaries highlighting how design can make applications addictive. It is possible to devise countless ways to captivate users, keeping them glued to your application. The primary benefits of this approach are pushing more ads to users or spying on them to build a profile for sale to the highest bidder. However, these are shortsighted goals and tactics. Awareness is growing among people, who now understand that if the product is free, they themselves are the product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, there is a trend towards paying for software nowadays, as demonstrated by the growth of SaaS products, consumers’ willingness to pay for digital content on platforms like Netflix, Apple+, and others, and the increased use of cloud-only products such as the popular design tool Figma. Such services depend less on ad revenue and more on providing quality products and delightful experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Users of these services have demonstrated that they are not only willing to pay for quality products and services but will also remain loyal to the company long-term. This contrasts with the software of the past, which would be uninstalled as soon as users had finished their intended tasks. In an era when the cost of acquiring customers is skyrocketing, wouldn’t you prefer to be the one retaining customers for the long haul?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ethics encompass the principles and values that guide human behaviour and decision-making, with a focus on concepts such as fairness, justice, and moral obligation. Ethics inspire individuals and organisations to contemplate the wider implications of their actions on others and the environment. By embracing these values, we can forge the kind of societies in which we yearn to live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As UX designers, we now hold immense power and the capacity to shape the digital worlds we increasingly inhabit. It is time for us to take responsibility for our actions, learn from the best practices, and strive to create a positive impact that fosters long-term well-being. Let us seize this opportunity, embrace our ethical obligations, and design a brighter future for all.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/the-eight-rules-of-ethics-for-ux-designers/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/the-eight-rules-of-ethics-for-ux-designers/</guid>
        
        <category>ux</category>
        
        
        <category>Ideas</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Fixing Censorship with Web3</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s important to keep striving for better models of censorship that can benefit society without infringing on individual rights and freedoms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Censorship has been around as long as information has been recorded and shared. Different groups, including religious authorities, governments, and corporations, have used censorship as a way to control what people can see and hear, sometimes for legitimate reasons but often to influence public opinion in their favour. It’s important to keep striving for better models of censorship that can benefit society without infringing on individual rights and freedoms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The emergence of both Web3 and AI presents an opportunity to find new solutions to this problem. These two fields intersect and could potentially lead to innovative approaches that balance the need for censorship with respect for individual liberties. The following is such an idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-need-for-a-redesign&quot;&gt;The Need for a Redesign&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The shortcomings of the current censorship system have led to a demand for a new approach. To illustrate this, consider a tech company that creates a massive social media platform with over a billion users across several countries like Twitter or Facebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this platform, let’s take one example of a video that was actually posted by a user that depicted the burning of an American flag. This is very likely to offend some users who may hail from the country that the flag represents. The offended users have a few options at their disposal. They may respond to the initial post and ask the user to take down the post because they’re offended, or, they may report the post to the platform for being offensive. The platform then decides whether the post is required to be taken down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then some form of the following decision tree ensues within the department of the social media platform in charge of handling such user reports:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is the post in line with the published set of standards related to posting content on the platform?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Was the first user right to post the content?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Was the second user right to be offended by the content?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is the offensiveness “sufficient” to warrant the removal of the post?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How much of a political or economic backlash will the platform face if it chooses to leave the post online or take it down?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider another example that occurred more recently. The artist Lindsay Mills shared a photo of her baby on various social media platforms. The photo showed the mother and baby, with only the baby’s butt visible. While some platforms allowed the photo to remain, one platform not only removed the post but also banned Mills’ account. This decision was made by an algorithm without human involvement, and appeals to restore the account were unsuccessful. The incident gained attention because Mills is married to Edward Snowden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These examples demonstrate the gray areas surrounding censorship, as society was divided on the appropriate course of action in each case. They highlight the problems with the mechanisms behind censorship, as corporations hold significant influence over society but are not elected to make these decisions.:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the following questions arise:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Will the platform make a decision based on standards that have been clearly published?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What was considered during the setting of these standards?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Who was involved in setting these standards? Were the people that weighed in on the standards representative of the population of users that will eventually use it or was it more representative of the standards of the corporation and where it was founded?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Should the standards be the same across geographies and cultures? Is it a lowest-common-denominator approach that is safe for all or were other factors taken into account for setting these standards?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is the basis for judging whether the content that clearly lies in the grey areas should be taken down or not? Is it simply how large a body of people it offends? How is the voice expressing the minority opinion protected?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do these standards change based on who the audience is, by age, by gender, by their own level of maturity? Can a user have control over what they want to be able to see or not?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Can I make up my own mind after exposure to the said content?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Does it evolve as a society’s views on issues change over time? What doesn’t change?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How does the platform handle pressure from external entities such as influential people, large groups or even governments of countries? What are the concessions it will make in this regard?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The platform cannot avoid adopting a specific political viewpoint because there’s no way around it. But if it holds any political leaning too strongly, it may loose users to rival platforms that do the same thing but only differ in their political ideologies. This is exactly what happened when Twitter decided to de-platform Trump. The problem with this then is it creates echo chambers where users are surrounded only by people that agree with them and view anyone with an alternative viewpoint as the other. We loose the public town squares where ideas are debated which is essential to building stable societies with moderate political leanings instead of societies that may erupt into civil wars at any moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, we are entrusting the responsibility of making decisions beneficial for society as a whole to a corporation whose sole purpose is generating profits for its shareholders. The mechanism does not allow for the consideration of societal well-being, as corporations must prioritise profits and their ability to sustain losses in a confrontation with political figures or governments pressuring them to make specific decisions. A single misstep can lead to lawsuits that could bankrupt the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When did it become a tech company’s responsibility to determine censorship implementation on a platform? Why do we accept this as the only approach when tech companies have consistently demonstrated their inadequacy in handling the responsibility of building good societies?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-decentralised-solution&quot;&gt;A Decentralised Solution&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A more effective approach would be to begin with the recognition that free speech is a fundamental right for all individuals. From this foundation, the solution should not focus on prohibiting certain forms of expression, but rather on preventing individuals from encountering offensive content. Although the distinction may appear subtle, the solutions for each approach differ significantly. By focusing on the latter, several benefits arise, as outlined below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The fundamental right to freedom of speech is maintained with no one being de-platformed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The user can control what they want to be exposed to or not be exposed to on an individual level and it can change over time on an individual basis&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;No other individual or entity dictates the standards for determining what someone should or should not be exposed to&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This system cannot be corrupted by external forces putting pressure on any single body&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While researching how a solution for this could work, the movie industry stood out as having a model that we could build upon. The film industry rates movies with suitability ratings like “PG-13,” indicating whether it’s appropriate for viewers aged 13 or older, and streaming services like Netflix provide additional information such as “Contains adult themes” or “Has crude humor” to help audiences make informed decisions. Even if two audiences are demographically identical, they may choose differently based on their preferences. This model has been effective in movies, so what if it was applied to content on the internet with the necessary modifications?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One potential approach is to assign tags to all posts on a fictional social media platform that describe the content. Viewers could then apply filters based on these tags to allow or prevent the content from appearing in their timeline. This central idea serves as the starting point for outlining how such a system could operate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-1-tagging-the-content&quot;&gt;Step 1: Tagging the content&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While AI models had to be trained to properly identify content in the beginning, the models have become pretty good at this task today. Now the model can be tested against the content to produce the right tags in the content. This is true for text, audio or video based content and across languages. So in the first pass, any new content that’s posted on a platform can be processed through AI models first to create a tag cloud for the content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tags can be improved upon by groups of people post the initial stage to provide an additional layer of meaning through the lens of different individuals. This should happen over time as well so as to not allow the meaning of the content to stagnate in time as the same content could change its relevance at a different point in time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-2-setting-up-filters&quot;&gt;Step 2: Setting up filters&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the receiving end of the content pipeline, the users need to mark content that they find offensive. But this process could be explicitly done with the user flagging some content as offensive, but also could be done through observing the viewing patterns such as the user scrolling past the content faster than they do on other content or hitting the ‘skip’ or ‘stop’ buttons on videos. One may argue that platforms like YouTube are already doing some version of this, but there are two big differences. Firstly, the data is maintained in a silo on the YouTube servers and not by the users themselves. Secondly, the goal of these platforms is self-serving and to increase viewership on the platform, not to do what the user wants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the above process gets better over time, users could also adopt filter sets from other pre-built filters created by people they trust, as starting points for their own filters to achieve immediate relief. This set then gets modified with the users own interactions with various platforms over time using on-device AI engines that are becoming more and more prevalent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-3-viewing-content&quot;&gt;Step 3: Viewing content&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is probably the simplest part. There can be timelines titled “For You” which is a view that applies the preference filters on the content being viewed and a second timeline titled, “Unfiltered” which shows all the content on the timeline if the user so wishes. This again is not even a new mechanism as most content platforms already use such devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-solution-for-the-age-of-ai-and-web3&quot;&gt;A Solution for the Age of AI and Web3&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While thinking through the solutions here, it was clear that the solution to the problem of censorship is not based on the imagining of technologies that don’t yet exist but the repurposing of those that already do. So why hasn’t it been done yet? I believe there are two reasons. Firstly, as anyone in software can tell you, the higher the amount of input you require from a user, the lower it’s adoption rate is going to be. So a self-learning system like AI or ML was necessary to exist for this to work otherwise it would have been humanly impossible to build a system that works. Secondly, the filters and learnings that a company like YouTube would develop about it’s user’s preferences were guarded as intellectual property of the company and not shared with even the user. So a decentralised system like Web3 needed to exist for such a system to work across the web.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re living in some really interesting times when these kinds of ideas will suddenly come to life because of the fertile ground created by AI and decentralisation that have culminated to put the user at the centre of the technological universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are obviously a lot more steps and nuances to consider when building this system, for example, how would such a system work for children and those that are not as tech savvy or even handle content that is clearly illegal across all nations. But I’m sure there are smarter people that could propose better ideas based on the foundation that has been proposed here. I just didn’t want to write an article pointing out all the problems without at least proposing a potentially better solution. If you are interested in discussing any of the ideas proposed here a little further, please do reach out.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/censoring-censorship/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/censoring-censorship/</guid>
        
        <category>opinion</category>
        
        <category>decentralisation</category>
        
        <category>web3</category>
        
        <category>design</category>
        
        
        <category>Ideas</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Seven Structural Elements to Keep in Mind for Web3 UX Design</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The structure of web3 influences the design of the applications&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/b1EKFhTJfdk?si=4zbUpZP9iV4fz326&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Web3 is a decentralised internet powered by cryptography and blockchain technology that allows for transacting with any entity in the world without the need for trusted middle men. It has specific uses in fields where having a trusted third-party middleman may prove to be corruptible, inefficient or expensive. But far too often UX designers are starting from equivalents in Web2 creating poor user experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;unique-elements&quot;&gt;Unique Elements&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several effects that the difference between these two structures affect the UX of applications built on top and the following are some main differences that UX designers must account for while designing Web3 applications:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1--decentralisation-is-slow-and-expensive&quot;&gt;1.  DECENTRALISATION IS SLOW AND EXPENSIVE&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since nodes in Web3 are distributed and are of different technical capabilities, data transmission across the network takes a lot of time compared to centralised systems. These processes can cause delays on the application layer, making them slow and expensive. In order to combat this, transactions are bunched up together before being written to the blockchain as a single write operation if far less expensive than several transactions writing the same amount of data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s therefore essential for a UX designer designing applications to decide which data needs to be written to the blockchain and also when in a user’s sessions that needs to happen. For instance, in building a decentralised version of Instagram, would you record every “like” of the user as they occur, or collect all of them and commit them only at the end of the user’s session?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many applications also adopt a Web2.5 design approach, where less critical interactions such as “likes” are stored on a centralised server for faster processing, while more critical data, such as who posted which picture, is written to the blockchain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there may other approaches that suit your applications and the right solution would entirely depend on the specifics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-the-blockchain-has-the-data&quot;&gt;2. THE BLOCKCHAIN HAS THE DATA&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most surprising ideas to me was that in the Web2 world, an application typically includes both a front-end and a back-end/storage layer delivered as an app. However, with data and storage openly available on a blockchain, the user interface and user experience &lt;strong&gt;is&lt;/strong&gt; the application. This means that someone else could write a new UX layer for the same data, and the user could choose which application they prefer, losing nothing when switching between apps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what’s the knock-on effect of this? It makes the UX layer super competitive, and the quality of experiences will only improve going forward. The app no longer stands for how well it manages to hoard and guard user data, but rather how good the experience and community behind it are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-its-community-owned&quot;&gt;3. IT’S COMMUNITY OWNED&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike products and services in Web2 that are owned by corporations driven by the interests of investors and shareholders, Web3 has “projects” and “protocols” that are owned by communities, not individuals, due to the philosophy of decentralisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there are participants attempting to amass wealth rather than distribute it to the community, more and more projects are evaluated on their decentralisation and ownership distribution. This impacts how things are designed because in traditional Web2 UX design, a good designer tries to balance the user’s needs against the needs of the company. However, in Web3, the success of the project is aligned with its users, as they hold the tokens and assign them their value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With data no longer locked into an app residing in a database, it brings honesty to the equation. Apps that prioritise user interests will win in the future. App that use dark UX patterns to deceive users will not be successful in Web3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-no-communication-channels-exist-yet&quot;&gt;4. NO COMMUNICATION CHANNELS EXIST, YET&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Web3, there is a lack of email or chat communication tools for peer-to-peer communication, and there is no de-facto protocol that can be assumed to be universally subscribed to such as email in Web2. Although tools like Push protocol and EthMail exist, they are not yet widely used and cannot be relied on for communication. This means that if someone buys something from your Web3 marketplace, there is currently no way to follow up with them to update them on the status of their purchase or to fix any issues, and they must come back and check with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asking for their email address is not always an option, as it could compromise their pseudonymity, allowing you to connect their email address to their wallet and potentially uncover all their blockchain activities. Therefore, it is important to design around this depending on the context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I did on one project where a certain process would take upwards of a few days to complete was to allow the user to download a calendar appointment that stated when they needed to come back and check on the status of this process. You just need to be innovative about how to solve these kinds of problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-the-wallet-is-everything&quot;&gt;5. THE WALLET IS EVERYTHING&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Web3, everything is based on cryptography using the concept of a pair of public and private keys. This provides users with pseudonymity, but not anonymity, in an otherwise transparent and open world. These keys are essential not only for authorising payments but also for verifying wallet ownership, interacting with smart contracts and linking all purchases to the wallet. Essentially, everything is connected to the wallet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this user-facing aspect of Web3 is largely unfamiliar to most people. Although it is vitally important to understand, most people do not know what these keys are. Losing or exposing the private key can result in the loss of all assets tied to it. Therefore, this area requires considerable design intervention to help people understand the significance of the keys, the right way to generate key pairs and the proper ways to store and protect them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then comes the usage of the wallet itself. It is used to sign messages from applications to authenticate yourself and also authorise transactions being made on your behalf. But these messages keep popping up with messages asking you permission for something reminding me of the early days of Windows 10 where the user kept getting asked to authorise even the most banal tasks. A lot more polish is required to only seek the user’s attention when you absolutely need it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The technology is still so new that sometimes the messages from the underlying stack are exposed to the user, and they are presented with only hexadecimal code, asking them to sign the transactions. Wallet developers have a lot of work to do to make this a lot more user-friendly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;6-smart-contracts-rule&quot;&gt;6. SMART CONTRACTS RULE&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is another concept in Web3 that has no equivalent in Web2. Smart Contracts are computer essentially programs that run on a network that was created to enforce an agreement between two parties. This means that two parties can rely on a transaction completing as agreed without the need for third-party guarantors and any associated expenses or delays, making transactions more efficient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, since Smart Contracts are written in code and they can be difficult for people to understand. Although the code behind these contracts can be viewed on blockchain explorers, more work needs to be done to make them accessible to the mainstream. When this happens, it will revolutionise everything!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;7-censorship-is-done-differently&quot;&gt;7. CENSORSHIP IS DONE DIFFERENTLY&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Web2, platforms that are owned by individuals or a small group have another problem in that they are also held responsible for implementing the censorship on them. In theory this sounds okay and the obvious thing to do, but if you explore this question more closely, there are many problems with this supposition:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They may very well be ill-suited to doing the job and may end up censoring things that shouldn’t have been censored excluding ideas that shouldn’t be excluded.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They have no option but to impose their world views on their systems and if they have a very large world-wide user-base, they will essentially be imposing their views on all of them superseding what’s culturally right.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Because they’re a central authority that can make these changes, they may be pressured by external individuals or groups to impose censorship that they themselves may not agree with.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There is always the question of “But what about the children?” that sneaks into every conversation about censorship and since there’s no argument against that, the lowest common denominator is set as the bar.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The political leanings of a platform have been the reason for new ones to be setup creating silos and echo chambers that only confirm your already held beliefs without public discourse or the meeting of minds in the middle. This technology has the potential to fracture societies instead of bringing them together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Web3 has a different architecture that does not have central authorities that can censor others, making it a haven for free speech absolutists. Adults who believe they should be exposed to all kinds of ideas to progress in life can do so without censorship. For individuals who want a certain level of censorship, they can choose to use a filter and block certain types of content. This step allows individuals to make their own choices without resorting to drastic measures of stifling someone’s voice or de-platforming them. Although it is not a whole solution, it is a step in the right direction. A lot of work has to be done in this field in terms of making this UX better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A decentralised internet can solve a lot of the issues that plague the world right now and give rise to new ways of interacting with others around the world. For this to become a reality, it needs mass adoption and the only thing stopping it is the complexity. User Experience designers can make a huge difference to adoption by making things much simpler for the everyday user. So if you’re a designer on this journey, kudos to you, you’re making a huge difference to the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, things need to be evaluated from the ground up based on the underlying decentralised architecture in order to deliver superlative experiences that are either at par or even better than the Web2 versions as this is indeed possible.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/seven-structural-elements-to-keep-in-mind-for-web3-ux-design/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/seven-structural-elements-to-keep-in-mind-for-web3-ux-design/</guid>
        
        <category>ux</category>
        
        <category>web3</category>
        
        <category>decentralisation</category>
        
        <category>design</category>
        
        
        <category>Ideas</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
